First of all, welcome to first encounter
official classes.
And uh
I think you know today is the day of
Lord Chaitanya.
Uh Lord Chaitanya was conceived today,
enlightened today, and passed away
today.
So, all the virtue we do is like a
million times more.
I don't know. Rama can tell exactly how
much.
But uh
It's a good day to have a I think the
first class of this particular series.
Um
We went to Tucson uh the last three or
four days getting poked and prodded by
doctors and dentists and
other kinds of things to see if we're
still alive.
So, and uh
And we had a chance to drive by the uh
place where the teaching will take place
in October. I think most of you know
this course will be repeated
in October uh over a four-day weekend,
Columbus Day weekend.
Uh
and their crew, I think Gail is in
charge of that, but they found a very
nice place. And we found out where it
was and we decided to drive by it.
And it's really beautiful. It's the
it's called the Muse.
Right?
And it's apparently it's an old YMCA
uh on Fifth Street, right off of Fourth
Street in Tucson. Fourth Street, I guess
you know, but I just found out it's the
it's like the happening street in in
Tucson. It's where all the students
come. It's like right across the street
from the university and then it's like a
mall in Santa Cruz or something or the
East Village.
Except it's only a few blocks long. And
uh
And um
so, we drove by and it's really
beautiful. The gym is really beautiful.
Uh it's not really a gym, it's this huge
beautiful place and it's broken up into
different
uh rooms now and um
we also saw a big sign that said uh
rooms are ready.
So, we figured the three jewels can go
in there afterwards.
Uh
or maybe before. We're going to talk
about that tomorrow maybe.
Anyway, we got the rooms and everything.
And uh I think it'd be a good area.
Uh we also did the jogging to work.
We did some newspaper and radio
interviews about the uh
about the three-year retreat and I guess
the
the newspaper thing came out
the last few days.
And then we went to do a radio interview
and the guy was very excited. He's going
to run it for 5 days in a row. Uh
he he did it like five times over the
normal length and then he wants to do it
for a whole week. And then he said in
October uh he'll do another long
interview for the teaching in October.
Uh the reason I'm telling you all this
is because you guys are going to be the
teachers
in October.
And uh I've gotten a lot of letters from
people and they've also been ads for the
tricycle and other places
uh
for that teaching. So, uh we expect I
don't know. We you expect you don't get
that many. So, maybe
uh
but I think there'll be at least 2 to
300 people there.
Uh and we have to be we'll be breaking
out in the mornings. The classes in the
mornings will be broken out into uh
smaller classes because we've got
feedback from people that when they come
into class and there's 300 people there
you don't feel like you're getting any
personal attention and you can't ask
questions and things like that.
So, what we're going to do in October in
the morning classes
uh they'll be broken out into those
little rooms in the Muse
space and they're very beautiful little
rooms um with nice hardwood floors.
They're used for dance and things like
that.
And each one of you who survive the next
10 classes
uh
will become a teacher.
And maybe we'll team up people in Paris.
If you're shy, I don't know.
Uh,
but my idea is to break out the morning
classes. You go, you get assigned,
you're going to have assigned two, five,
10, 15 students each.
And then you have to teach what I'm
about to teach. So that's like an
incentive
uh, for you guys to to do it seriously
now, okay? And I want everyone to try.
You know, I know a lot of you think,
"I'm not a teacher." or "I never did
that."
And uh
Like I remember the night that Punso
came into New York.
Pelo was there. The New York class the
first time. It was a really rainy night.
Only four people showed up for class.
And this guy named Punso, well, he
wasn't called Punso then, right?
And uh he walks in and he says, "I don't
know anything about that. I can't teach.
I don't know anything about this stuff."
Uh, now he's got a regular Friday night
class in New York with 70, 80 students
coming.
Uh, and there are many people like that.
So
I want all of you to be in the frame of
mind that uh you're going to be teaching
this. And even people who listen to the
tape or get the video
two years from now,
uh you have to be thinking in terms of
teaching what I'm about to teach. The
whole idea is the lineage.
And we have to continue the lineage. Um
So please keep that in mind. You're also
going to get homeworks and you'll also
be responsible to do a quiz when you get
into class
uh, on Wednesday night.
We'll be going Wednesday night and and
Saturday afternoons.
And you should get the schedule from
Ellen cuz there's a break there for some
vacation and uh somebody named Dolly
Bowman or something like that. And uh
we'll be at Kinner P'shat and we'll be
busy with with those things.
Um
how many people weren't here for the
last
for the first half of this class?
Oh, boy. Really?
Where's the guy who didn't get
Ooh. Okay. We'll have to do a short
summary.
Uh, we did the first half of this first
class just for good luck on the lawn on
the night we got here, on the night we
broke the three year retreat.
Uh but I'll just do a summary I guess.
And then we'll go ahead. This class will
be about an hour and then a break for
Notice I said in about.
A break for uh refreshments.
And then we'll go for another hour. And
then um
after that
we're going to have a dinner for
everyone. So you're invited to dinner,
right? Is that
And uh after that from 6:00 to 7:00 or
however late we go
um
we're going to do the great Sojong
ceremony. Sojong means to once a year
commemorate has instituted uh
a a purification ceremony. And this was
done in the great Tantric colleges in
Tibet once a year.
And instead of the usual monks Sojong
which takes place every twice a month
uh where you get to purify all the vows
that you broke in the last 2 weeks.
Um in Sojong Chenmo you go through all
your vows which means your Pratimoksha
vows, your Bodhisattva vows, and your
Tantric vows. So what I'd like to ask is
during dinner
uh everyone write down six pieces of
paper, six slips of paper, okay?
There'll be the three
best things you did in the last year for
your Pratimoksha vows, your Bodhisattva
vows, and your Tantric vows.
And then there'll be the worst three
things you did in the last year for your
for the same thing.
If you don't have the Tantric vows or
Bodhisattva vows, then just write it
down for your Pratimoksha vows. If you
don't even have Pratimoksha vows
just the best of the 10 non-virtues that
you avoided and the worst of the 10
non-virtues that you did, okay?
And we'll burn them
uh in the fireplace from 6:00 to 7:00.
And then from 7:00 on I think we have
some kind of a celebration starting
from singing and reciting and something
like that.
Flying.
So, uh
So, I
guess we'll just go down the book today.
So, I guess it looks like I have to go
over a little bit of the last class. Um
And that's just to summarize how we got
the book that you're about to study.
I got to give you the title of the book
first.
This is going to be, as you know, the
ACI courses are English track
or English and Tibetan track. And so,
I'll be writing Tibetan words up here.
You're not responsible for them if you
don't want to be.
Um but,
you know, most of us have found out that
when you get under pressure
at the Muse space in Tucson and some
smart guy from Fairbanks, Alaska is
asking you a question, you can spit out
some Tibetan and answer him.
And he doesn't know what it means and
you don't know what it means, but
it's not really saving you.
So, maybe you should write down a little
bit of just so you cover yourself.
Uh so, I'll be doing it in Tibetan. Now,
since we're kind of into Sanskrit,
especially guys who are doing uh tantric
starting the tantric series next year,
and a lot of the texts that we'll be
using for the
seven-year five- to seven-year tantric
series will be Sanskrit, which then
reached Tibetan. So,
uh I'm going to be writing Sanskrit
also, and you should just start getting
used to it. So, there'll be a Sanskrit
track, too. Some people might want to do
Sanskrit only
in English. Some people might want to do
English and Tibetan. Some people might
want to do all three. If the guy from
Fairbanks knows Tibetan, you can throw
out some Sanskrit
and
get him off your back.
All right.
Yeah, it should really come.
He's getting caught.
Uh I'll say there's Sanskrit in that and
then I'd like you to repeat it. It puts
a seed in your mind
and uh
even if you don't get it in this
Sanskrit practice this lifetime, you
might get it the next time or the
lifetime. Say Uttara. Uttara. Tantra.
Tantra. And you have to get used to the
difference in in When you're doing
Sanskrit, the difference between a and a
is very important.
So, listen to how I say it. I don't say
Uttara. I say Uttara.
Say Uttara. Uttara. Don't say Tantra.
Say Tantra. Tantra. Yeah.
It becomes important because like the
second half of the name of the scripture
is Shastra.
Say Shastra. Shastra. Shastra. Shastra.
It's like ah instead of ah.
I'll tell you why. Shastra means
commentary. Shastra means a sword that
you kill somebody with.
So, you wouldn't want to teach somebody
Uttara Tantra Shastra.
You'd want to teach them Uttara Tantra
Shastra.
Okay? Uh cuz you don't want to kill
them, you want to teach them.
Uh
but that's a very good example for
distinguishing between what we call
Mahayana and Hinayana. And we'll get
better at that as the time goes.
Uh
there's a word before the Uttara Tantra
which is Mahayana.
And I'll do it in Sanskrit this way.
Those of you in the
feeling brave for the Sanskrit.
Tell me if I'm going too normally.
I'm going to Sanskrit this one for you.
Uh
Say Maha. Maha. Yana. Yana. If anyone
ever wants to change this to
Mahayano. Mahayano.
Tantra. Tantra. I'm sorry. Uttara.
Uttara. Tantra. Tantra. Shastra.
Shastra.
Listen to the Sanskrit. Uh I'm going to
write it in the back for you.
Say give. Give. Give. Uh it gets cut off
a bit. So, I might as well teach you
right. I mean, we're out here in the
desert. Nobody's listening. You. You.
Nama. Nama. You. You. Nama. Nama.
Um you might notice that the difference
is a little shorter.
Uh
And I'm going to give you the full of
that in a moment. But, just to go
through the words,
Mahayano you know means big vehicle,
type of chamber.
Big capacity.
Uh Uh,
you're going to get a commentary
by one of Geshe Kunga's students, Geshe
Dakpa. I'm going to give you the
reading. You don't get the reading today
cuz I couldn't finish it cuz of doctors
and dentists and everything else.
Uh,
but Geshe Dakpa says it's Maha because
of seven different reasons.
The big means seven different things.
So, this book is all about the big
capacity people. Basically, it's people
who are willing to work for the
happiness of every living creature in
the universe
and aren't concerned only with
themselves.
Okay? So, you go from one to infinite
number of beings if you step onto
Mahayana.
So, that's the meaning of Mahayana.
Mahayana, okay?
Uttara
means uh, Lama.
And that's the same as Guru Lama. Lama
means
what?
Teacher. Highest. Uh, but literally it
means higher one.
Higher one, okay? So, Uttara means
higher one.
Uh, Geshe Dakpa when he explains Uttara
in his commentary, he says it's
Anuttara.
Anuttara. Anuttara,
some of you may know, is the name of the
highest tantric teachings, the highest
group of tantric teachings out of the
four.
And it means Lama Meppa.
Above Lama.
Meaning, there's nobody Lama above this
book, okay? Like, this is the highest
book, Lama, okay?
Um,
so, Uttara means Anuttara means nothing
higher than that, okay?
Tantra
here, which is Gyü in Tibetan,
uh,
and that's a lineage. You do Gyü lineage
in tantric colleges and you do tantric
colleges, which means a lineage, okay?
Or it can mean tantra also, okay?
Um,
tantra usually means the secret
teachings of Buddhism as opposed to open
teachings of Buddhism.
Uh,
here it has nothing to do with that.
We're not teaching secret books today.
Okay? This tantra is not a tantra.
Okay? This book is called a tantra
because of the meaning of series, tantra
means a series.
Like a lineage. So, when you say uh
Yube Lama, for example, which is a
different spelling,
it means the lamas of our lineage. Okay.
So, tantra means that.
Uh and as we mentioned in in English,
the word tantra has come into the words
tenuous
and tenacity and tendon
and distension extension meaning
stretched out
into a series or a line. Okay.
Uh
shastra shastra means a cutter,
which means uh a commentary, an
explainer of analysis. It breaks the It
breaks the meaning up.
So, really what this book is about
is an ex- it's an explanation
of the series,
which is Uttara,
and which is about
helping all living creatures, Mahayana.
So, it's a commentary on the series,
which is Uttara, and it's about helping
uh big big vehicle, big capacity, people
who can help all the people in the
world. By the way, Mah comes into
English with a prenasal Mah.
The H changes to G G.
And the M turns into you get magnitude
out of here, Magna Carta,
uh magnificent, things like that, okay,
from the Mahayana.
Um
Now, we got to go to the Uttara. Why is
it called uh highest? And you see some
people even like 500 years ago, they're
saying, "Oh, it's the best book of all."
So, it's called Uttara Tantra.
Uh that's not what Gelsang Gyatso says.
Gelsang Gyatso says, "Think of highest
in terms of ultimate.
And think of ultimate in terms of the
thing that comes at the end."
Okay. Like we have penultimate in
English and ultimate,
meaning the thing just before the end
and the thing at the end. So, think of
Uttara
as ultimate, but in the a of the very
last teaching, the very last teaching.
So really this is an explanation
of the lab latter part
of the teaching.
Okay? That's the meaning of the name of
this book.
What teaching is he talking about?
It We We talked about it already, right?
You guys already know. Um
You know that Lord Buddha turned the
wheel three times.
Uh first time Lord Buddha appeared as a
Is it three times? Yes.
No, four?
Let's see.
The first time he turned the wheel as uh
mainly he talked just after he became
enlightened he talked the four noble
truths about suffering and how to get
out of suffering
and that kind of thing. He didn't say
much about emptiness.
The second turning of the wheel, he came
on big time on emptiness. He said,
"Everything's empty.
Nothing in the world has any quality on
its own. This pen
doesn't have any quality of its own. You
don't have any quality of your own. Your
mind doesn't have any quality of its
own. The world doesn't have any quality
of its own. Nothing has any quality of
its own. So where's the pen?
You could do mu ma ya ma ta.
This pen is not blue, right?
That one.
Yim ma ta?
Oh, mu ma yim ma ta. So it is blue.
Yeah. Mu ma ya ma ta.
So it has a characteristic of being
blue, right?
Mhm, chi che.
Wa ta. It doesn't have a characteristic
of being blue.
Oh, it doesn't have any characteristic
at all.
Well, it doesn't have any
quality that belongs to itself.
Yeah. So the blue doesn't belong to the
pen?
Yeah.
Mu ma ya ma ta. So the pen doesn't have
blue?
Chi che. He said good.
It's still a dream.
You know, he said it doesn't have any
character except it's sound. And
obviously Lord Buddha meant that
the blueness of this pen is coming from
me,
from me personally.
How could it be coming from me if
everybody sees it the same?
Hello.
Uh How could it be coming from you if
everybody sees it as blue? We all share
the same karma to see it as blue. Yeah,
you all did the same action in the past
to see it as blue.
So, that means that there could be a
person without a karma?
Yes. Like who?
Sure. Uh if there were a blind person in
the room. Yeah, a blind person. They
wouldn't see it. Or a color blind
person. Yeah. They just would see it as
gray.
That's because they have something wrong
with them and not because it's not blue,
you see?
So, that proves in a way that the blue
is coming from me. It's very
interesting.
It's very
profound. So, then in the third turning
of the wheel, Lord Buddha said, "Oh, I'm
sorry. I didn't mean that.
Some stuff has its own characteristics
and some stuff has it."
Like pens are obviously blue.
And especially the fact that it writes.
It must have a quality of writing in it,
right?
Being able to write must be in the pen.
If it works, if I can draw something
with it, the ability to write something
should be inside this
this plastic cylinder, right?
Like Lord Buddha,
how do you say it? He did a New York
Times correction.
Uh
You ever seen it? On the third page of
the New York Times, they have a little
column and they say, "We made these
boo-boos last week."
It's very honest in a way. Cuz people
don't normally do that.
And um
So, Lord Buddha said, "Oh, I made a
mistake, you know." People said, "People
cannot turn Some of the people from the
second turning of the wheel cannot
accept this. This is too much.
Are Are telling me this pen doesn't
write by itself?
He said
he judged the student and he said this
student can't handle what I'm teaching.
I better back off and he backed off of
it.
Then so he said, "Yeah, you're right.
The blue pen is blue. The characteristic
of being blue belongs to the pen.
Writing belongs to the pen. I'm sorry. I
was just being figurative. I was just
trying to shake everybody up a bit,
okay?"
And then he passed away and he left He
left it like that.
Then for 2 and 1/2 thousand years people
have to figure out Did he mean it when
he said he didn't mean it?
Okay?
Or did he mean it when he said he meant
it?
You see?
And for 2 and 1/2 thousand years people
have struggled with this question. So we
have a Madhyamaka tantra. That's a real
tantra. That's the real tantra of the
angel called Jam pal yang or
we call gentle voice.
And in that book it says
uh there'll be uh a monk named Asanga
will come along and he'll straighten
everything out.
You know, he'll say, "Lord Buddha didn't
mean that or didn't mean that." Or you
know, "Lord Buddha was telling the truth
in the second turning of the wheel." Or
"Lord Buddha was telling the truth in
the third turning of the wheel."
But you notice nobody has much trouble
with the first turning of the wheel.
Why?
He didn't really talk so explicitly
about emptiness.
Lord Buddha didn't really Emptiness is
where people get screwed up, right?
Before they hit tantra.
Right? But emptiness is where people get
confused.
So Lord Buddha taught emptiness in the
second and the third turning of the
wheel.
So if you wanted to write a book about
clarifying that series of teachings,
first, second, third turning of the
wheels, what would you call the book?
We call it the Sutra Shastra.
I'm going to explain the latter part,
the ultimate part of the series.
Meaning those series of three three
turnings of the wheel. So
I think if you ask a thousand people you
might not hear this explanation once.
It's very beautiful in Gelsang Gyatso
and it's hard to get out of Gelsang
Gyatso. And it will be in your reading
if the reading ever occurs.
But you'll see.
So, in a way Gelsang Gyatso
a song of master song is offering to
explain the confusing latter part of
that series. And that's why it's called
what?
Mahayana. And Mahayana Mahayana is not
included in Shravakayana.
Uh
which of the three turnings of the wheel
is Mahayana?
Mahayana.
Uh Kor Sem
The Wheel of the Three Turnings of
Which one of the three is Mahayana?
Huh?
All three included in Mahayana.
Right.
The teaching of the four truths and the
teaching of the four noble truths.
You're telling me that
the teaching on the four truths is
Mahayana?
Yes, it's included in Mahayana.
Right.
Included in Mahayana in the Mahayana
So, everything included in Mahayana is
Mahayana?
I would think so.
The teaching of the four noble truths
and the teaching of the four noble
truths. Let's take the series of the
path that are intended for people of
lesser capacity. Mahayana in the
Mahayana
So, I guess it's Mahayana, right?
It's part of it's included in the
All right. It's included in Mahayana,
right?
Right.
What about your Yanas? So, we're
supposed to practice that by itself?
No. You practice that in Mahayana in the
Mahayana? Yeah, cuz it's Mahayana.
No, it doesn't does All of Shravakayana
is included in Mahayana?
Is your foot part of your body?
Is that how you figure it out that you
still have a body?
Anyway, Mahayana stressed in the last
two turns of the Yanas.
I mean, she take the four great schools
of ancient India.
The two Mahayana schools I treated in
the last. So, it would make sense to add
a word to the title of our book, which
is
Mahayana Uttara Tantra Shastra.
And he's explaining Shastra means he's
trying to clarify what happened in the
latter part of the Buddhist teachings.
We had another uh explanation of this
series thing. Do you remember remember?
What was it?
Chung thing. Say it? Chung thing.
Uh what's the Was it the Chung thing?
I think so.
Yeah, I think Chung thing is what it
was.
We're going to talk a little bit about
how this book came to be, how this book
came into our world, the Uttara Tantra
Shastra. So, so everybody calls it
Uttara Tantra Shastra, but you know that
that's just the short name, right? Like
people in Tibet call it Gyü Lama. I said
Gyü Lama. Gyü Lama. That just means the
latter part of the series.
It leaves out Mahayana and leaves out
explanation. So, people get confused
about what the meaning is.
But everybody in Tibet calls it Gyü
Lama. Say Gyü Lama. Gyü Lama. Gyü Lama.
Gyü Lama. Uttara Tantra. Uttara Tantra.
Okay.
Um
it's one of the five great books of
Maitreya. Maitreya
gave
Arya Sangha five great books when Arya
Sangha showed up in his heaven one day.
Uh
and you guys know the story. I think
I'll run over it real fast, but I think
the people who weren't here should get a
tape of something cuz the whole story is
But uh to put it briefly, Arya Sangha
tried for 12 years. He didn't do a
three-year retreat, he did a 12-year
retreat,
which is really supposed to be ideal.
But we don't pray that Joe thinks it's
not ideal.
Uh
and he in those 12 years he stayed in uh
solitary in a cave, and he tried to get
a vision, he tried to meet Maitreya. And
he worked really hard to meet Maitreya.
Uh
at the end of the
retreat, he still hadn't seen my chair.
He gave up. He went out. He went to the
nearest town.
Um
on the way to town he saw a dog that had
been run over by a car and it was cut
here and like squirming
after a
and the lower part of the body had been
completely eaten away by maggots and
they were starting to attack the
They were starting to attack the upper
part of the body.
And then he knelt down and he looked at
the maggots and said, "I got to get the
maggots off the dog and the dog will
probably die."
Then he had a thought, "If I take the
maggots off the magazine will die."
So
he said, "You know what I'll do? I'll
I'll get a knife. I'll cut a big piece
of flesh out of my thigh
and I'll set it on the ground and then
I'll put the maggots on the flesh and it
won't die and the dog will be cured."
So he goes to town, he gets a big razor
blade, he cuts a big piece of meat off
his thigh
and he sets it on the ground and he
starts to reach for the maggots and he
says, "If I
pick them up, I'll crush them
with my fingers." So he says,
"I'll just lick them off."
So he's kind of grossed out. So he goes
to the dog.
And he puts his finger out
and he goes down and then
you know the end of the story. He He
licks the ground and he looks up and
there's my chair.
And
he says to
It's interesting how Yeshe Sangye's
reaction is sort of interesting. He He
gives him a line of verse uh
which is to say, you know, "Where the
hell have you been for 12 years, you
know?"
You know, I was like he's not all like
lovey-dovey with my chair. He's sort of
pissed off with my chair.
He's like
"You know, are you going to show me
You're going to come to me in the first
week, you know, right?
12 years later, you know, now you're
showing I'm already out of the retreat.
I left the retreat, you know, now you're
showing up to me?"
And my chair says, "You couldn't see me.
I was there the whole time. I was
sitting right next to you. Sometimes,
when you create this route and you spout
during the mantras,
uh you spit on me.
You know, I had to like dodge you all
the time. And
and
Aryasanga says, "I don't believe you're
in the cave. If you're in the cave, I
would have seen you."
And
Maitreya says, "Oh, so everybody sees
things the same way, right?"
And then Aryasanga says, "I think so. I
would have seen you, you know, if you
were there."
So, Maitreya says, "Okay, well then you
take me up on your shoulders and you
dance around town with me on your
shoulders. Let's see. Let's see what
happens."
And he does that and he dances around
town. And you know the story. Everyone
thinks Aryasanga is crazy cuz he's
dancing around town with nothing on his
shoulders.
And he's saying, "Look on my shoulders.
Look on my shoulders. I got Maitreya on
my shoulders."
Uh and you know the story. One old lady,
one barmaid,
sees uh
a puppy.
Just a little puppy on one shoulder. And
uh
one uh like neighbor, construction
neighbor, sees uh
What is he seeing on his
Oh, he sees his toe hanging off right
here.
And
And as a result, they both think
something I can't do now. Something you
can't do now.
Uh
But in a way, the story of how Oh, and
then the story goes that uh Maitreya
says, "Now that you believe me, do you
believe me?" And Aryasanga says, "Yeah,
okay. I believe you."
He said, "Well, what did Why did you try
to get to me anyway? What did you want,
you know?" And Aryasanga says, "I was
trying to figure out emptiness.
The
the perfection wisdom sutras. And I
couldn't do it. I couldn't figure it
out.
Like he I figured out all those other
books. I understand the middle way of
the books. I understand all the other
Mahayana books. I just can't get this
emptiness thing."
So, Maitreya says, "Okay, grab onto my
robes and we'll take a trip." And he
flies into the Tushita heaven.
Uh I just read a book this morning that
says
that Aryasanga was able to get back on
his own.
Uh
So,
he flies to this and he spends
part of the morning there
and 50 years pass in human time.
And during that time
I'm sorry, my teacher teaches him these
five great books on
Maitreya.
Uh
because Aryasanga says, "How am I going
to teach everybody what you taught me?"
Because Maitreya teaches him the whole
perfection of wisdom sutras, which is
like
it's about 25-30 volumes. It's like
3,000 pages or something
in an in an hour in the morning.
Uh so he said, "How can I go back to
earth and teach people this?
Can you give me something shorter?"
So he gives him these five very short
books. Um
I thought I would list them again. Well,
I don't know if we have time to list
them. Yeah, let's do it anyway.
Okay.
Um
Look at that.
I'm shortening the for our convenience.
So we say "che" Che. "nyi" Nyi. "non"
Non. "che" Che. "nyi" Nyi. "non" Non. Uh
You have my "che"?
Dharma. "Che nyi non" means Here it
means things. Things.
"Che nyi non" means Dharma.
Is it that?
Yeah, emptiness or the way things are.
You see, when you add "nyi" to it, it
means the way things are. So you got
things and the way things are.
"Non che" means distinguishing. Like
this is the
things and this is the way things are.
Okay, so it's a book about
distinguishing things from the way
things are.
I'm going to go through the progression
of the five books. Um Maitreya taught
the five books to Asanga in in an order.
And the purpose of the order is to get
your mind from simple emptiness up to
ultimate emptiness.
Okay?
So we're going from
sort of a
What do you call it? Trendy
interpretation of emptiness up to the
real one
through the five books.
Uh and I'm going to be quoting from
Gyaltsab Je's commentary.
And we'll talk about who he is later.
Uh but he's a student of Gyaltsab Je.
Who
He says if you want to know what things
means here, it means the things that
appear to you.
Things as they appear to you.
Like Mr. Ben, am I separate from you?
Yes. No.
Yes and no.
In what way?
Uh Ultimately or conventionally? Good.
Good. Good.
Uh
It's a great question but stops the
debate.
Uh
Me and my nature, so we are separate and
not conventional.
Separate and not.
Okay, so I'm over here and you're over
there. You're not um
Yeah, that's a good way to say it. Okay?
I mean, conventionally you could say I'm
over here and he's over there and we're
separate.
And there's nothing wrong with that. You
know, I can't build a house.
Ben can build a house.
That's the stuff. We we can't be the
same person else I could just copy what
he does.
So, we're separate.
Um
But are we separate in an ultimate
sense?
Why not?
And and the answer in the lower schools,
okay, we're talking mind only school, is
that my
this person that I'm seeing is a result
of a seed in my own mind. In that sense,
we're not separate. You know? I see a
person. There's a functioning real
talking, working, living person out
there and I'm over here and I'm
different.
But I see that person because of a seed
in my own mind.
So, in a sense, that person is a
projection of my own mind. In that
sense, we're not we're not separate.
Um
So, chunya here
means what Ben called
uh
conventionally separate.
Okay? I mean, we seem to be separate
from each other, right? There's space
between us.
That's the way things look.
And then chunya means the way things
really are, which is that even though it
seems that I'm separate from Ben,
uh everything about Ben, every single
characteristic of Ben and Ben himself is
a projection of my own mind
because I want to project that, right?
No,
forced to. Yeah.
You also have to say forced to,
okay?
My karmic seeds,
what how I treated people in the past is
forcing me to see a person, good, bad,
mixed,
like that. It's totally up to my own
how I treat other people, okay? And
that's the genius of the things that
just seem to appear around us. So, che
nyi means the way things appear.
Che nyi means the way the real
situation.
What Why is nam jor a good
word to put in here?
Anybody?
It might make sense with how the two
things are going to be distinguished.
You got to distinguish between them.
You see? You got to distinguish between
them.
Like like if you get angry at somebody,
you fail to distinguish.
You think that person exists there. You
don't realize it's coming out of your
own mind. And if you get angry, what's
going to happen?
It's going to
happen again. And then what's going to
happen,
you god damn well better be able to
differentiate nam jor
between the way things look and the way
things really are. Okay? So, that's a
great book, right?
I think. Um
what else does it say in there?
Okay, that's the first
first book.
Finally, you went up to Arya Sangha and
said,
"When you say man and you are separate,
uh
conventionally,
um
is it real?"
You know, he said real. So, he said
real.
And uh
It depends on how you define real,
right?
If real means the way I I think of it
normally,
or usually as it comes to my mind,
would you say it's real?
No.
Yeah, I think no. If you can still get
upset by anybody, the answer is no.
Okay? Meaning you you don't really
understand how they are. So, in this
first book,
Maitreya didn't clarify
the meaning of real as far as meaning
the man.
Okay? He kind of fudged it. He kind of
fudged it.
You know, he said, "The appearance is
I could say it's real." "Oh, real in
every way?" "Oh, you could sort of say
that."
Okay? So, you see where Maitreya is
trying to
He tried to put out his first book a
little more What do you call it?
Doubleday instead of MSTV.
He's trying to reach
a broad audience that
And he's And he's watering it down a
little bit for the broad audience, okay?
And that's the way an author would do
that, right? He's got to present it in
an easy way.
So, when people got into, you know, "Is
man real?" and then he said, "Well,
yeah, pretty real."
Okay.
Okay, say "Middle time middle." Middle
time middle.
Middle means uh the center of something,
and especially of a
along a line,
like the center of a line. So, it's like
left-wing
politicians and right-wing politicians.
And then, what do you call them in the
middle? Moderate. Moderates.
Yeah. As opposed to center. You see,
center mean mean to
as opposed to center in the meaning of
the center of a circle.
This is not that.
Uh whenever we say "u"
in this sense, it means the center of a
of two extremes, like on a horizontal
line, okay?
Um
Tommy is the extremes.
Okay, the two extremes.
Namjay means
distinguishing distinguishing between
the center and the extremes. Okay.
What's the center and what are the
extremes? Let's see what you guys think.
Oh, okay.
Uh
in this book my chair goes one more step
and he says, uh you know that thing I
talked about in the last book I wrote?
I want to clarify it a little bit.
Some things have their own
characteristics and some things don't.
Let's divide it into three.
Okay? So, those of you who studied the
Diamond Course of Buddhism book
or uh the ACI 15 course
um these are the three what we call the
three characteristics of things that
uh
are are taught by the Mind Only school.
And I'll just go through them very
briefly.
Uh
does this thing really work the way it
seems? According to the Mind Only
school, Mr. Stulberg.
Yes. Yeah. It writes.
It writes on the board. So, it's real in
that sense. It's true. It exists truly.
It's real in that sense. It writes.
Okay?
Uh
emptiness itself, Mr. Stulberg. If you
see emptiness
uh
can it really allow you to get
enlightened quickly and um see your
future lives for example?
Yes. Yeah, so it functions. So those two
things, ultimate reality
and working things, changing things,
normal stuff in the world, we lump them
together and in this book
Maitreya says they exist
truly, really.
You know, they really exist.
But now, what about the
root beer club?
That's
waiting for me behind this blackboard.
What about the root beer club
that Christie won't let me drink?
It's waiting for me behind this
blackboard.
Where is that? How real is that?
I don't see it. Even if it was there, I
couldn't drink it.
So,
uh
That's like what what we call an
imaginary thing.
And and in the Mind Only school, those
don't count as having as being real,
true, having their own characteristics,
etc.
So we divide all things into three.
It's we divide between the
the center and the extremes, you know?
It would be too extreme to say nothing
exists. It'd be too extreme to say
nothing has its own characteristic,
okay?
Pens have their own and all the other
stuff we normally deal with has their
own characteristics.
Emptiness must have some kind of power,
some kind of characteristic, cuz when
you see it all this great stuff happens
to you.
But what use is a is a root beer club
that doesn't, you know, that you're just
thinking of that you know's not there?
You know, no function, no benefit. That
we throw into unreal things. So that's
dividing the middle from the extremes in
this case.
So Lord Maitreya introduces those three
ideas of the Mind Only school. Some
stuff really exists, some stuff doesn't
really exist, okay?
So we're still in the Mind Only school
with these two books, the first two
books. We're getting people to emptiness
gradually.
Which means we're accepting which one of
the three turns of the wheel
is this thing.
Remember the first turn of the wheel he
just sat down with his four five guys
who had been his tiger cub friends in
his past life
and he said
look, this is a real bad life we got to
get out of this thing.
And in the second turn of the wheel he
says everything's empty.
This pen's not blue.
Then in the third wheel he blocks and
says I'm sorry now of course it's blue.
What was my original question? Oh, which
wheel are we
Which turn of the wheel are we in now?
The third. The third cuz he's laughing.
He's laughing. He said it's all
something's right and something's not,
you know?
Lord Buddha didn't mean it in the second
turn of the wheel. Lord Buddha Buddha
was just being extreme. Why? Shake
people up a little bit and wake them up.
Okay.
Sometimes that's necessary.
Oh.
Yes you Michael? Yeah. You said that
there are three things coming um
and then you went on to say that some
stuff exists and some stuff doesn't.
According to that school.
Those are two things. Things that exist
and things that don't. What's the third
thing? Now
two of the groups really exist which is
A changing things and B emptiness.
And then one of the groups doesn't
really exist which is my root teacher's
view.
view. Okay. Yeah. Of course we could
change that, you know?
Can you find a seat for me?
What's the other one?
You can come out of there.
There you go.
Say Dode again. Dode Dode Dode
Dode means sutras, meaning the teachings
of Lord
especially the open teachings.
Dode means more or less the Sutra
Pitaka, meaning the basket.
Uh the whole collection of open
teachings.
Gyen means Gyen means an ornament like
uh this uh
bracelet. That would be a gyen.
And sometimes when you write a book
explaining someone else's teachings, you
call it like a jewel for those
teachings, meaning
you know, who might have made Lord
Buddha's sutras better,
but I can sort of pretty it up a little
bit with my explanation.
And that's why it's called Dode Gyen,
Sutra Alamkara. I'm thinking Krystyna
can make the Sanskrit
words for everybody who wants them, and
then we can just pass them out cuz I
don't think we have time to
to do three classes tomorrow.
Uh but anybody who wants the Sanskrit
can you put pressure on her?
I still think it's good for you to have
in your pocket when you walk into the
wide
YMCA in Tucson.
There's like five shark guys like Brian
Smith. You guys got to watch out for
them.
I speak them all mostly.
Winston. Sorry.
Now, this is how Galsan Gyatso describes
it. Look, we're on the third book. This
is how Galsan Gyatso describes it.
Uh
Nyi nang dam pa'i bka'
He says
in the third book,
uh my teacher didn't
didn't deny
uh
that emptiness is real.
Okay?
Uh
But now the wording has changed, right?
In the first two books, he's saying he
is real.
You know?
Like he's a changing thing, he's like a
person. It's real It has its own
characteristics.
But his description of the third book is
In the third book,
my teacher doesn't deny it's real.
Meaning what?
It's a mind god.
You mean what? It probably is, but it's
a double negative. He doesn't say it's
real.
You see? In the first two books, he says
Michael's breathing.
You know? As I see him, he's breathing.
But when it gets to the third book, now
in the third book, he doesn't
he doesn't deny he's real.
Which implies he doesn't say he's real.
Okay? That's like a typical mantra.
Okay.
Then he says uh "Three types of root
precepts of the top means of the day."
Then he starts to teach my teacher
starts to teach, "How can you wake up
the compassion in your own mind?
How can you wake up bodhicitta in your
own mind?"
So he's getting heavily into bodhicitta.
What How do How do you become
bodhicitta? Rik chepa means everybody
has that seed in them.
And that's the big That's the big
subject that the book we're going to
study. If someone comes up to you the
first day in the YMCA and says,
"Well, what are we going to study?" You
say, "Oh, Buddha nature."
You know? This book's all about Buddha
nature. There's a Buddha inside you.
Okay? How do you wake it up? How do you
realize it? Okay, rik chepa.
Um
Then he says uh "Chapter 7 talked about
common ground and capable of doing so."
How do you get your bodhicitta qualities
to get bigger and bigger, higher and
higher?
That's another subject of this third
book.
Do ja shin je sem pa top gyepa ten na
brilliance.
What are some sneaky ways of collecting
students
and attracting them to these ideas?
Okay? Like movies or music or
yoga business.
It's beautiful. Desert.
How do you attract students?
Okay.
And then he says um
Then he says an interesting thing. The
other day he says Chung sum wo day dag
yi ni don't just talk about doing that
at some point. Thank you. He says
the first three books of my trail
present the ultimate
in a way which is comfortable
for the student.
Okay? Like they present the ultimate
but in a way which is comfortable for
those particular people.
Key, but
che tong day wang gi tsang gi du big don
by don dam ba sel wa me day.
But they don't clearly talk about
emptiness in the sense that not sky any
quality of self.
Okay?
Now that in itself is an implication.
What?
What's he implying? That it's not
last to do.
He says, "Now the first three, they
mention the ultimate reality
but just in sort of a schmoozy way.
In a fluffy fluffy way. Mhm.
Because the student can't handle it.
But they don't clearly state, 'Look,
nothing's got any quality of self. This
thing's not blue by itself.
This thing's only blue because you're
asleep to me.
Anything you see about me is coming from
you.
Okay? Anything you see about what I say
or how I act is coming from you.
Same with the pen. Same with your own
mind.
Same with your world. Same with the last
guy who cut you off in traffic.
Okay?
Why get mad at him? Take care of the
real thing.
Shantideva says, "Don't get mad at the
baseball bat, get mad at the
the guy who's swinging it. Come on." You
know what I mean? Which is who?
Who?
Me.
Okay.
Uh
We got two more books to show.
All right, this is all the history part.
It's a little boring, but we'll get to
the fun stuff next class, right?
Uh
Maybe it's not so boring. Say, "We don't
talk again." We don't talk again. We
don't talk again. We don't talk again.
Uh it says here it's Abhisamayalankara.
Um
This book by my trainer, we study it for
the first 12 years in the monastery.
When you enter the getse course,
and around age 13 you're you're taught
at 13 to 15 you're taught basic logic
and how to debate. Then when you're
deemed fit to enter the debating ground,
you're allowed to start studying the
first book. And this is the first book
we study. 12 years
on this book. It's 50 pages long.
Okay? This this you're you're covering
an average of four pages a year.
And you spend about 10 hours a day
working on it.
It's really intense. I mean, this book
is really intense.
Uh
What does book number four Oh, if you
translated it would it would be the
ornament or the jewel of realizations.
Window means realizations
and gem means the jewel. Again, like an
ornament.
I'll just quote Gampopa.
Don't many people talk to people. The
ultimate view of emptiness worldview.
That's what we call our organization,
right? That's what it means.
All the All the
All the organizations are all under this
big umbrella of worldview. Don't talk to
people means the ultimate worldview.
Yana Yana sum.
This book talks about the ultimate
worldview over and over and over again.
Okay? This book talks about the ultimate
worldview of emptiness and karma over
and over and over again.
Narkey
Narkey means
What?
What? What? What?
Gampopa.
They're not many things to go on about,
but the main thing that this book
teaches is a peculiar idea
about three shades of emptiness.
We haven't gotten to it. We're not going
to get to it in this course. Okay?
But there's an idea that there are three
kind of like degrees of emptiness, three
shades of emptiness. Like the emptiness
of a person
in its subtle form and its gross form.
And the emptiness of this house
in its gross form and subtle form.
Uh that you could that you could put
sort of shades of emptiness. And then
you could divide everybody in the world
into those people who can see the
easiest kind of emptiness. And those
people who can see the medium kind of
emptiness. And those bodhisattvas who
can see the ultimate kind of emptiness.
And you can kind of shade emptiness into
three different paths, three different
ways. Okay? What we call listener,
self-made Buddha, and bodhisattva. Okay?
And that This book is mainly devoted to
that idea.
Is that a
Madhyamaka idea?
Yeah, it is a high school idea.
But is it the highest part of the high
school idea? No.
No. It's the lower half of the high
school.
Which is called, do you know?
Svatantrika. Svatantrika. Meaning,
what do you call it?
Independent school. Independent.
Of course it is not.
Independent school. So they accept this
idea of three shades of emptiness.
But the highest highest high school,
Prasangika,
the consequence school, they don't
accept that.
Which probably means what book number
five is going to be.
Yeah, Gyulama.
Just say Gyulama.
Gyulama really presents emptiness in its
right form, highest emptiness. I'll call
you also again.
This is the eighth chapter of Gyulama.
Chapter chapter Gyulama tantra they mean
the Mahayana tantra shastra, Gyulama,
number eight of Tsongkhapa's combat
is presented for people who are already
used to the mind only ideas.
Like if you've been studying all those
mind only books, the first three books,
right, of the five,
and you got used to the idea of
emptiness
in a sort of easy way, a walking way,
a walking way, then you've been set up
for the Gyulama.
So Gyulama
is for them.
It says something which should be taught
later on to people who have already been
dragged through the first three books.
Okay? They understand
emptiness roughly. They understand the
thing about them being
created
by the seeds in my mind. And in that
sense we're not separate. That's a lower
emptiness.
That's a lower emptiness.
Okay?
Why? Guess. It has to do with kun-zhi.
Yeah, nice.
Okay? I'll say it again.
Uh, the mind only school, the first
three books, they only get as far as
beings being projected by the seeds in
my mind.
Okay?
But the assumption is the seeds in my
mind are real.
The projector is real.
Okay, everything I'm seeing, everything
I experience, even myself, that's a
projection.
But that special box out of which
reality is pouring
in my own mind, that box has got to be
real.
That much has got to be real, okay?
And then
in the fifth book, they come along and
say, "Uh-uh.
Even that box is your projection.
The projector is your projection, okay?"
And then we got to get we got to talk
about that. That's a big argument in the
Guhyasamaja. That's a big subject in the
Guhyasamaja.
And the point is that half the people
you teach it to at the YMCA,
they never heard of this idea of stuff
coming out of a box in your mind.
And you got to judge the people. You got
to say, "Am I going to present
Guhyasamaja the the way the
first three books were presented?" Or
maybe even before that, you know? And
you got to you'll be in a stuck in the
same situation as Lord Buddha.
You'll be stuck with five or 10 students
from Kansas maybe or wherever.
Except now the people I meet from Kansas
are really smart, but anyway.
Um
You know, and you got to judge you right
on the spot you'll start to say, "Now
look, Guhyasamaja is talking about this
kun-zhi thing and and you know the
kun-zhi is just a projection too and
this is a projection." And they're going
to be like,
you know, and then you're going to have
to back up. Uh uh
third turning of the wheel, back up,
right? Oh, yeah yeah, I'm sorry, I
didn't mean that. Um well, there's this
Buddhism thing, you know, and and got to
be nice to people and uh
you know, and you
you learn my healthy out of that and uh
Yeah, yeah, yeah,
yeah.
See, you got Yeah, you got to take out
your pen and start. And you know, you'll
be stuck in that position like boom from
the first moment you look in their
faces, you start to talk about Gyalwa,
and then you'll adjust.
You know, you'll do tongue aid.
You'll go to the
to wherever their level is, you'll have
to adjust to that. You know, that's the
part of our job. That's what we do for a
living, right? We just adjust to the
audience at the moment. Um
So, anyway, Gyalwa
in the fifth book
Maitreya says, "Look, even the
projectors are projecting."
Even the projectors are projecting.
Okay.
And then he really begins to describe
what's literal and what's not literal in
the fifth book, okay?
So, since you guys are so great, we're
going straight to the fifth book.
Uh, which is Gyalwa.
Um
We're going to take a break, but just
before that I want to say one more
thing.
When Asanga came back to Earth
and all his friends were
dead. He's like Rip Van Winkle, right?
I know that I was only gone for two
years and a half of them were dead. But
anyway,
uh
And he comes back and he says, "How am I
going to teach this to people, you
know?" And he gets eight good students
and they go out in the middle of
nowhere, like Bodh Gaya Arizona.
You know, he says, "I don't care. Eight
good students is enough."
He takes them out in the middle of
nowhere. It's a forest in Magadha state
in India. And they go out in the forest,
they go out in the middle like just a
tent in the middle of the street, you
know, and he says,
I'll get these eight people
to understand what this is all about.
And he really works hard on them. He
gets them up to saba,
which is almost up to seeing emptiness
directly.
And he gets them up to where they can
read other people's minds.
And you know, it's not like you wake up
one morning and you can read what
somebody else wants for breakfast
uh
directly,
but you wake up and you have a sense.
It's just like a sense.
Like you're kind of thinking, maybe
Thelma would like tuna fish for lunch,
you know.
And it's just a
a sense that you have, you know? And you
make it and then she's really happy and
it's like the beginning of
Shen Sem Shi Pa,
which is reading other people's minds.
And then as you practice more and more
and more, it becomes more and more uh
clear in your own mind to where you can
actually hear them talking in their own
mind.
But it starts with some kind of a
instinct about what other people need or
want or
And um if you're going to teach people
like at the YMCA,
uh
it's really helpful. You can imagine how
helpful it'd be. Like you before you
walk into the room, you know whether
you're going to have to back up or not.
You see what I mean?
And so for a teacher, it's really
useful. So, Arya Sangha was working
really hard on his first eight students
to get them up to this level where they
could
at least have a strong instinct for what
those people need, their their students
need. And you know the story, eventually
he got invited to a king's palace. Um
The king wants to test him cuz he
doesn't believe he's such a great yogi.
And he puts him through these tests. Uh
and you know some of the tests, but I'll
repeat one. He takes a golden urn made
of pure gold.
And inside he puts a bunch of smog and
pus and poo-poo and pee-pee. And then on
the top he puts about an inch of honey.
And then he he like says to Arya Sangha,
"Guess what I got in the pot?"
And uh
And Arya Sangha says, "I know what's in
the pot and I wouldn't eat it, you
know?"
And so the king is like, "Well, anybody
could tell that kind of thing."
Um
And then the king asks Arya Sanga six
questions mentally.
In his mind.
About the perfection of wisdom sutras.
Like he beamed six questions to Arya
Sanga.
Uh, we're going to cover those
after the break. So, you've got to come
back, right?
Uh,
so take a break for 10, 15 minutes. And
just relax and uh
uh,
go to the bathroom.
It's a small bathroom.
Yeah. And there's there's a big uh thing
of cookies in there.
And well, and then just relax and come
back in 15.
Okay.